Contact Information email: ikuperwajs@nyu.eduweb: ionatankuperwajs.github.io

phone: 425-283-2084

post: 4 Washington Place #809

New York, NY 10003

Research Interests My research interests lie at the intersection of cognitive science and computer science. I primarily use tools from artificial intelligence and reinforcement learning to infer what algorithms people use to plan sequences of actions in complex environments.

Education

Ph.D. Candidate in Neural Science

2018-Present

2014-2018

New York University (New York, NY) Systems, Cognition, and Computation Track

B.A. in Neuroscience, Computer Science, & Mathematics

Macalester College (St. Paul, MN)

Honors in Mathematics, Magna Cum Laude

Summer Schools

IBRO-Simons Computational Neuroscience Imbizo

2018

Cape Town, South Africa

Research Experience

Graduate Research: Human planning in large state spaces

Center for Neural Science, New York University

Advisor: Wei Ji Ma 2019-Present

Investigating the cognitive processes underlying sequential planning by collecting large-scale behavioral data in a combinatorial game of intermediate complexity. Particular focus on developing theoretical models for integration between prospective and retrospective decision-making and training deep neural networks to reproduce human play.

Eigen-distortions of stacked, local gain control

Lab for Computational Vision, New York University

Advisor: Eero P. Simoncelli

2018-2019

Trained an optimized end-to-end image compression model based on the concept of divisive normalization in biological systems. Then identified the eigenvalues corresponding to the model-predicted most and least noticeable image distortions, testing the model's ability to mimic human perceptual sensitivity.

Lightweight, flexible visualization and analysis of FreeSurfer surfaces

Computational Visual Neuroscience Lab, University of Minnesota

Advisor: Kendrick N. Kay

2016-2018

Developed statistical and image processing tools for visualization and analysis of high-resolution fMRI data, utilizing FreeSurfer to analyze preprocessed cortical surfaces and decode fine-scale neural activity.

Bayesian inference of neural activity and connectivity from all-optical interrogation of a neural circuit

Janelia Research Campus, Howard Hughes Medical Institute

Advisor: Srinivas C. Turaga

Summer 2017

Worked on a variational autoencoder-based framework for mapping neural connectivity from population activity measurements by calcium imaging combined with cellular resolution optogenetic activity perturbations.

Dynamic network model and attractor states of the C. elegans connectome

LINK-Group, Semmelweis University

Advisor: Péter Csermely

Spring 2017

Built a network model to simulate global activity states of the C. elegans nervous system to search for stable attractor states and map those to distinct behavioral patterns.

Neural processing of the optic flow field

Computational Neurogimaging Lab, New York University

Advisor: David J. Heeger

Summer 2016

Implemented a novel perceptual model for optic flow based on motion without movement to determine that the human visual system estimates heading direction and angular velocity from the evolution of the optic flow field over time.

Publications

Conference articles and abstracts

• Kuperwajs, I., van Opheusden, B., & Ma, W.J. (2019). Prospective planning and retrospective learning in a large-scale combinatorial game. *Cognitive Computational Neuroscience*. pdf

Honors & Awards

National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship 2020-2023

Computational Psychology

Three years of NSF financial support for outstanding graduate students in research-based STEM disciplines.

Trainee Travel Grant

2019

Cognitive Computational Neuroscience (CCN)

National Science Foundation funding for highly-rated submissions.

Henry Mitchell McCracken Fellowship

2018

Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, New York University Multi-year full funding support for doctoral students.

National Honor Society Member

2018

Epsilon of Minnesota, Phi Beta Kappa

Inducted students have a GPA in the upper 12 percent of their graduating class, a commitment to liberal studies, and knowledge of mathematics and a foreign language.

Outstanding Graduate Award

2018

 $Neuroscience\ Department,\ Macalester\ College$

Awarded by faculty to the graduating senior with the highest achievement and promise in the field.

Undergraduate Travel Grant

2018

Computational and Systems Neuroscience (Cosyne)

Coverage of travel and meeting attendance costs for undergraduate students with a strong interest in neuroscience.

Dean's List 2014-2018

Macalester College

Awarded to full-time students with a semester GPA of at least 3.75.

Undergraduate Scholars Program

2017

Janelia Research Campus, Howard Hughes Medical Institute

10-week summer program aimed at well-prepared, independent, and committed undergraduate students with significant research experience.

Men's Soccer Academic All-Conference Team

2015-2017

Minnesota Intercollegiate Athletic Conference

Awarded to student-athletes with a minimum career GPA of 3.5 who meet sport-specific athletic requirements.

National Science Foundation Undergraduate Research Program

2016

Center for Neural Science, New York University

10-week summer program for undergraduates with a strong interest in neuroscience and a research-centered career.

DeWitt Wallace Distinguished Scholar

2014

Macalester College

4-year merit scholarship (\$64,000) awarded to academically excellent applicants.

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant, New York University

• Mathematical Tools for Neural and Cognitive Science (NEURL-GA 2201) F 19

Teaching Assistant, Macalester College

• Algorithm Design and Analysis (COMP 221)

F 17, S 18

• Brain, Mind, and Behavior (PSYC 180)

F 16

• Core Concepts in Computer Science (COMP 123)

S 16, F 16

Talks

- Center for Neural Science, New York University
 Human planning in large state spaces

Concepts and Categories Seminar Series

November 2019

Department of Psychology, New York University

• Combinatorial planning

Artificial and Biological Computation Lab Meeting Center for Neural Science, New York University June 2019

• Visualization and analysis of high-resolution fMRI

Honors Thesis Defense

May 2018

Department of Mathematics, Macalester College

• Bayesian inference of neural circuit properties from calcium imaging data

J-Theory Meeting

August 2017

Janelia Research Campus, Howard Hughes Medical Institute

• A dynamic network model for the C. elegans connectome Link-Group Meeting

May 2017

Department of Medical Chemistry, Semmelweis University

 Neural processing of the optic flow field SURP Symposium
 Center for Neural Science, New York University

July 2016

Poster Presentations

- Prospective planning and retrospective learning in a large-scale combinatorial game Cognitive Computational Neuroscience September 2019 Berlin, Germany

Technical Skills

Programming: Comfortable in Python and MATLAB. Familiar with R, Java, C, C++, HTML/CSS, and bash.

Coursework: Graduate-level courses in mathematical tools for neuroscience, machine learning, Bayesian and cognitive modeling, and cellular and systems neuroscience.

Methodologies: Behavioral modeling, reinforcement learning, statistical inference, deep learning.

Lab: Experience with human psychophysics and fMRI.

Other Skills: Experience with object-oriented programming, parallel programming, computer vision, network science.

Languages: Fully proficient in English, Spanish, and Hebrew.

Service & Activities

- Scientist Action and Advocacy Network (ScAAN) 2018-Present President of a pro-bono science group. Work typically consists of evidence-based reports and data analysis/visualization for partner non-profit organizations.
- Commencement Speaker Selection Committee 2018
 One of four student representatives nominated to select the Macalester College commencement speaker.
- Macalester Software Development Organization (MacHack) 2015-2018 Hosted events and gatherings for students interested in programming.
- Macalester College Varsity Men's Soccer Team 2014-2018 Member of the nationally-ranked men's soccer team, won conference title and made an NCAA tournament appearance in 2015.